Finding Aid for University School (University of Michigan) Records, 1920-1975 (bulk 1930-1960)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University School (University of Michigan) records 1920-1975, 1930-1960
University of Michigan. University School.
8 linear feet
Demonstration school operated by the University of Michigan School of Education, 1924-1969. Records include annual reports, staff bulletins, publicity, photographs, faculty minutes, building plans, and curriculum material; also records pertaining to the closing of the schools, and a historical file on the founding of the schools including correspondence of Allen S. Whitney.
87302 Bimu C203 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group (Donor 1220 ) has come to the library in periodic accessions.
The collection is open for research.
During the early 1920s, the School of Education faculty began to discuss the possibility of establishing a high school within the School of Education. The original objectives of the high school were to serve as a laboratory for scientific study of secondary school problems and to furnish facilities for observational work and directed teaching to approximately one hundred university students each semester.
In 1922 the Legislature approved $525,000 for a high school building. In the fall of 1924, the school was opened to students in grades seven to twelve. There were 123 students the first year, with a limit set at 360. Students were grouped into homerooms by grade and after 1929, also by sex. Students had the same home room teacher for all six years (grade seven through twelve). Much of the student life was organized by homeroom: representation to Student Council, intra-mural sports, and various school and community service projects. Tuition for the high school was $15.00 per semester, with a limited number of scholarships available. The University High School was fully accredited by the University of Michigan and the North Central Association of College and Secondary Schools.
Six years later, in the fall of 1930, the University Elementary School opened with sixty five students between the ages of two-and-a-half and five-and-a-half. Each year, the next oldest age group was added until the school reached the sixth grade. The main focus of the school was educational research and the study of child development. The school was used as a demonstration center for educators in the newer practices of educating children. Tuition at the time of opening was $50 per semester for a full day session and $15.00 a semester for children on half-day session.
In 1955 the University High School and the University Elementary School were combined, to be known as the University Schools; Dr. Robert S. Fox was appointed director.
In the 1960s, the School of Education established new priorities and the decision was made to eliminate the University Schools. The last senior class graduated in 1968, although the high school continued for one more academic year. The elementary division closed its doors at the end of the 1969/70 school year.
Following the closing of University School the buildings were converted to administrative space and classrooms for the School of Education.
The records of the University Schools operated by the University of Michigan School of Education document the activities of the schools (elementary and high school), students, parents, alumni as well as the physical facilities of the schools. The records date from 1920 to 1975 although the bulk of the records cover the period from 1930 to 1966. The last vestiges of the schools closed after the 1969/70 academic year, but records relating to the renovation and remodeling of the school buildings are present through 1975.
The records were received in three accessions resulting in the creation of several series. Thus researchers will find some overlap within the various series, particularly the topical files and administrative files. The records are divided into eight series: Topical Files; University Elementary School Files; University High School Files; Administrative Files; Classroom Activities; Photographs; Historical Files; and Renovations and Architectural Drawings.
Subjects:
University Elementary School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Education, Elementary--Activity programs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
University of Michigan. School of Education.; University Elementary School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Education, Elementary--Activity programs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Elementary school teaching--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Whitney, Allen Sisson, 1857-1944.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (1.0 linear feet) contains information on the closing of the University Schools, alumni recollections, and minutes and newsletters of the Parent Teacher Association.
  - Administrative Committee Minutes
    - 1954-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1959-1967 (Box 1)
  - Alumni
    - Class of 1931 Questionnaire 1938 (Box 1)
    - Class Updates circa 1962 (Box 1)
      (class of 1941, 1942 1953)
    - Correspondence 1976 (Box 1)
    - Recollections circa 1967, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Faculty and Executive Committee Meeting Minutes 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Recollections circa 1968 (Box 1)
  - Minutes (miscellaneous) 1963-1968 (Box 1)
  - Parent Teacher Association (PTA)
    - Membership Lists 1958-1968 (Box 1)
      (scattered)
    - Minutes
      - 1934-1936 (Box 1)
      - 1946-1947 (Box 1)
      - 1948-1960 (Box 1)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 1)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 1)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
      - 1965-1967 (Box 1)
      - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - Newsletter 1957-1963, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - School Closing
    - General 1962-1969 (Box 1)
    - Academy for Education Development Report 1969 (Box 1)
      (recommendation on closing)
    - Appraisal Committee Report 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Closeout Activities 1963-1969 (Box 1)
    - External Review Committee 1968 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Committee 1963-1969 (Box 1)
    - News Clippings 1964-1969 (Box 1)
    - Parent's Committee Rebuttal 1969 (Box 1)
    - Protests 1962-1969 (Box 1)
    - Reunion 1968 (Box 1)
      (in conjunction with closing activities)
  - Social Values, Committee on 1956/57 (Box 1)
  - Statement of Purpose 1952-1960 (Box 1)
- University Elementary School Files
  The University Elementary Schools Files series (1.0 linear feet) documents the school through annual report files, faculty meeting minutes, and school policies. There is also a folder entitled "goals/purpose" that would be of interest to the researcher interested in the research focus of the University Elementary School.
  - Annual Report Files
    - 1930/31-1951/52, 23 folders (Box 2)
  - Budget Materials 1930-1939 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes
    - 1933/34 (Box 2)
    - 1934/35 (Box 2)
    - 1935/36 (Box 2)
    - 1937/38 (Box 2)
    - 1938/39 (Box 2)
    - 1941/42 (Box 2)
  - Goals/Purpose 1930-1937, 1944 (Box 2)
  - School Policies
    - 1932/33 (Box 2)
    - 1933/34 (Box 2)
    - 1934/35 (Box 2)
    - 1935/36 (Box 2)
    - 1936/37 (Box 2)
    - 1938/39 (Box 2)
    - 1941-1945 (Box 2)
    - 1946/47 (Box 2)
    - 1949/50 (Box 2)
- University High School Files
  The University High Schools Files series (3.5 linear feet) documents the social activities of the school through the "reports on assemblies" and the thirty year run of scrapbooks. The scrapbooks contain newspaper clippings of sports activities, community action, and notes on the alumni. There is information on the general curriculum as well as faculty minute meetings of the Junior High Division.
  - General 1920-1933 (Box 3)
  - Assemblies (report on)
    - 1929-1932 (Box 3)
    - 1932/33 (Box 3)
    - 1933/34 (Box 3)
    - 1934/35 (Box 3)
    - 1938-1942 (Box 3)
    - 1943-1952 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1926-1936 (Box 3)
  - Curriculum Committee 1949-1965 (Box 3)
  - Curriculum
    - Core Requirements 1964 (Box 3)
    - English circa 1945-1965 (Box 3)
    - Humanities 1960-1966 (Box 3)
    - Languages 1959-1965 (Box 3)
    - Physical Education 1955-1966 (Box 3)
    - Sciences 1957-1965 (Box 3)
    - Social Studies 1959-1966 (Box 3)
  - Goals/Purpose 1923-1930, 1952 (Box 3)
  - Homeroom (policies and procedures) 1960 (Box 3)
  - Junior High Division
    - Curriculum 1957-1969 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Meeting Minutes
      - 1957/58 (Box 3)
      - 1958/59 (Box 3)
      - 1959/60 (Box 3)
      - 1960/61 (Box 3)
      - 1961/62 (Box 3)
      - 1962/63 (Box 3)
      - 1963/64 (Box 3)
      - 1964/65 (Box 3)
      - 1965/66 (Box 3)
      - 1966/67 (Box 3)
    - Nuggets of News 1965 (newsletter) (Box 3)
    - Library 1936-1964 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1929/30 (Box 3)
    - 1930/31 (Box 3)
    - 1931/32 (Box 3)
    - 1932/33 (Box 3)
    - 1933/34 (Box 3)
    - 1934/35 (Box 3)
    - 1935/36 (Box 3)
    - 1936-1938 (Box 4)
    - 1938/39 (Box 4)
    - 1941/42 (Box 4)
    - 1943/44 (Box 4)
    - 1944/45 (Box 4)
    - 1945/46, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1946/47 (Box 4)
    - 1947/48 (Box 4)
    - 1948/49 (Box 4)
    - 1949/50 (Box 4)
    - 1950/51 (Box 4)
    - 1951/52 (Box 4)
    - 1952/53 (Box 4)
    - 1953/54 (Box 4)
    - 1954/55 (Box 5)
    - 1955/56 (Box 5)
    - 1959-1961, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Senior High Division
    - Faculty Meeting Minutes 1960-1968 (incomplete) (Box 5)
    - "In Imitation of Pepys" 1936 Class Project (Box 5)
  - Student Council Minutes 1933-1966 (Box 5)
  - Student Publications 1934-1939 (Box 5)
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files series (1.0 linear feet) contains information regarding school policies, administrative activities, faculty research, school programs, and an undated historical file. The records cover both the high school and elementary school.
  - Attendance List 1933 (Box 5)
    (attendees of UES and UHS)
  - Camp Ohiyesa
    - General 1963 (Box 5)
    - Log 1957 (grade seven) (Box 5)
  - Commencement Scrapbook 1929-1948 (Box 5)
  - Faculty Research Publications 1934-1966 (Box 5)
  - Historical Materials undated (Box 5)
  - Junior Trip 1964 (Box 5)
  - Programs and Invitations 1934-1940 (Box 6)
  - Sample Materials 1932/33 (administrative use) (Box 6)
  - Scheduled Programs 1938/39 (Box 6)
  - School Policies and Recommendations to Teachers 1949/50 (Box 6)
  - Sixth Grade Sports 1938 (Box 6)
  - Student Guides 1932/33, 1950 (Box 6)
  - Student Teaching (policies and procedures) 1964-1967 (Box 6)
  - Theses
    - "A Tentative Course of Study in Physical Education for Girls at University High School" by J. B. Saurborn 1933 (Box 6)
    - "An Analysis of Student Reactions to Eight Teaching Procedures used in the University High School Girl's Education Classes" by G. M. Penhale 1942 (Box 6)
  - University Elementary School Scrapbook 1930-1933 (Box 6)
- Classroom Activities
  The Classroom Activities series (1.0 linear feet) is divided into four subseries: Class Projects, Individual Projects, Curriculum Materials, and School-Wide Projects. The Class Projects subseries is comprised of stories, poems, and newsletters that were created as a group project. The projects are arranged by grade level, nursery through sixth grade. The Individual Projects are comprised of booklets made by students on a particular topic. Curriculum Materials are resources that were used and/or created by a teacher for a specific activity. The School-Wide Projects contains items not specific to a particular grade.
  - Class Projects
    - Nursery
      - "Ann's Book" 1939/40 (poems) (Box 6)
    - First Grade
      - "Cynthia's Story" 1940 (1st grade) (Box 6)
      - "The First Grade Story Book" 1936/37 (Box 6)
    - Second Grade
      - "A Bus Project" 1935 (Box 6)
      - "Ghost Stories and Others" 1941 (Box 6)
      - "My New Boots" 1943 (Box 6)
    - Third Grade
      - "Radio Time for Kiddies" 1936 (Box 6)
      - "Lots of Fun Magazine"
        - 1936/37 (Box 6)
        - 1938 (Box 6)
      - "Our Treasure Book of the Atlantic Ocean" 1939 (Box 6)
    - Third/Fourth Grade
      - "Book of the United States and its Possessions" 1941/42 (Box 6)
    - Fourth Grade Group
      - "Pleasure Time Book" 1937 (Box 6)
      - "Poem Book" 1946/47 (Box 6)
      - Different Things, 1937 (Box 6)
        (newspaper)
    - Fourth and Fifth Grade Group
      - "The Moon's Children" 1936 (Box 6)
    - Fourth-Sixth Grade Notebooks 1945/46 (Box 7)
    - Fifth Grade
      - "Facts and Fiction" 1938 (Box 7)
    - Fifth and Sixth Grade
      - Black Hawk magazine, 1943/47 (Box 7)
    - Sixth Grade
      - "Sports Down the Line" 1938 (Box 7)
      - Safety Exhibit 1937/38 (Box 7)
    - Late Childhood Division
      - "The Summer Star" 1936 (Box 7)
    - "Group 5"
      - "Squeaks and Buzzes" 1940 (Box 7)
        (re:inventions)
  - Individual Projects
    - Africa circa 1936 (Box 7)
    - Bridges circa 1936 (Box 7)
    - Flags circa 1940 (Box 7)
    - Home on the Range circa 1936 (Box 7)
    - Stories for Little Folks circa 1936 (Box 7)
    - The Erie Canal circa 1936 (Box 7)
  - Curriculum Materials
    - "An Experimental Hunch in Reading" 1938 (Box 7)
    - Cedar Lake Trip 1960 (Box 7)
    - Diary of Activities 1937 (group IV) (Box 7)
    - "Don't Laugh" 1940 (Box 7)
      (invention activity of group five)
    - Explore All 1964 (Box 7)
      (eighth grade program)
    - Field Courses 1939/40 (Box 7)
    - First Grade Reading Material 1933 (Box 7)
    - Mill Lake Outdoor Experience 1960 (Box 7)
    - Station TGR 1936 (Box 7)
      (developing a radio unit)
  - School-wide Projects
    - Monroe St. Publishing 1939 (Box 7)
      (class of 1946)
    - Songbooks circa 1936 (Box 7)
    - Wolverine, 1945-1946 (Box 7)
      (classroom news)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (0.5 linear feet) is comprised of negatives and black and white photographs of varying sizes. Many of the photographs have a corresponding negative in the negative folder. Most of the photographs depict the elementary school classroom of the late 1930s.
  - Negatives circa 1938-1959 (Box 7)
  - Photographs/Prints
    - Athletics undated (Box 7)
    - Classroom Activities circa 1938-1954, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Group Photographs 1938-1959 (Box 7)
      (includes slides)
    - Individual Portraits 1939 (Box 7)
    - Outdoor Activities 1948-1952, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Performances 1938-1950 and undated, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Student Council 1944-1945, 1955, circa 1958 (Box 7)
- Historical Files 1920-1968
  The Historical Files series (0.3 linear feet), 1920-1968, contains documents relating to the establishment and operation of the University Schools; some of these files were presumably used as background materials for some of the renovation work. Included are correspondence files, statistics and histories of the schools. Of particular note is the file of Allen S. Whitney's correspondence. The Whitney correspondence includes correspondence with Raleigh Schorling (first principal of the University School), and a letter from James B. Edmonson pertaining to the circumstances under which Whitney became the School's first dean.
  - Clippings 1954-1968 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence
    - Establishment of Schools and Construction of Buildings 1926-1947 (Box 8)
    - University Elementary School 1927-1955, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - University High School Closing 1946-1968 (Box 8)
    - Allen S. Whitney 1922-1949 (Box 8)
      (1st Dean of School of Education)
  - Statistics and Histories 1920-1954, undated (Box 8)
- Renovations and Architectural Drawings
  The records in the Renovations and Architectural Drawings series (0.7 linear feet) document the physical facilities for the schools and the rehabilitation and renovation of the buildings, which took place in two phases--the first between 1961 and 1962 and the second between 1970 and 1971. The series includes documents relating to the needs analysis conducted in preparation for the renovations. Material on the closure of the University School and the subsequent conversion to facilities for the School of Education is also included. The architectural drawings include floor plans and material on allocation of space. Some additional buildings utilized by the School of Education are also present.
  - Renovations
    - Needs Analysis
      - Classroom Data 1970 (Box 8)
      - Space Needs and Rehabilitation 1956-1965 (Box 8)
    - Phase I
      - Rehabilitation Conference Notes 1961-1962 (Box 8)
    - Phase II
      - Colvin, Robinson and Associates 1970-1971 (Box 8)
      - Construction Meeting Minutes 1970-1971 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence 1967-1975, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Project Meeting Notes 1970-1971 (Box 8)
      - Project Reports 1970-1971 (Box 8)
      - Renovation Program Statement 1970 (Box 8)
  - Architectural Drawings
    - Miscellaneous Buildings 1958-1961, undated (Box 8)
    - Photographs, 1957 (Box 8)
    - School of Education 1961-1971 (Box 8)
    - University Elementary School 1957-1970 (Box 8)
    - University High School 1927-1969 (Box 8)